There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Can’t live with them,
can’t live without them.
And yes, I’m talking
about teeth.
Did you know that chewing pressures
in the jaw can have neurological effects?
Here’s our first story.
Systematic reviews
and meta-analyses
have found that tooth loss,
or periodontitis,
is associated with
both cognitive impairment
and dementia.
Reverse causation might be
an intuitive explanation,
dementia leading to a decline
in oral hygiene,
but prospective studies
following people over time
have found that tooth loss
appears to predict
future cognitive decline,
and the more missing teeth,
the higher the associated risk.
Genetic determinants
of elevated periodontitis risk
do not appear
to be associated
with the development
of Alzheimer's disease,
suggesting the association
may be due
to shared
or confounding risk factors.
A poor diet
or low socioeconomic status
represent common pathways for
both tooth loss and dementia,
but even studies controlling
for confounding factors
found a connection
between tooth loss and dementia.
However, one factor that wasn't
controlled for was intelligence.
Those with higher IQ
are both more likely to floss,
and have fewer
tooth and gum problems
as well as have
a delayed onset
of clinically
detectable Alzheimer's
due to
a greater cognitive reserve.
Are there any
potential causal mechanisms
beyond the chronic inflammation?
If you induce periodontitis
in mice with P. gingivalis,
the keystone pathogen
in human periodontitis,
the bacteria
ends up in their brains
and triggers an increase
in the Alzheimer's-associated
plaque protein amyloid beta.
Since then,
evidence of the bacteria
has been found
in human Alzheimer's brains.
Clinical trials
are now underway
to see if blocking
its neurotoxic effects
will have
any therapeutic benefit.
A clue to
a stranger potential mechanism
was unearthed in
a subgroup analysis
of a tooth loss
and dementia meta-analysis.
Only tooth loss
among those without dentures
was associated with the
later development of dementia.
The same tooth loss
with dentures was not.
How does that make any sense?
A review entitled
"Mastication for the Mind"
compiled a number of studies
suggesting that chewing,
mastication in medical speak,
is somehow important
for proper brain function.
For example, the extraction
of teeth from aged mice
appears to upset
their memory and learning.
But maybe they're just upset,
in pain, inflamed,
from having their teeth removed.
A more convincing series
of experiments
compared mice
given food pellets
versus the same pellets
crushed into powder.
Those eating the "soft" diet,
the powdered diet,
also suffered a loss in memory
and learning capacity.
What does chewing
have to do with cognition?
Stick an ultrasound probe
on someone's head
and you can detect an increase
in cerebral blood flow
of the largest artery branch
in the brain
when they clench their jaw
or chew gum.
In an fMRI machine,
brain scans show
enhanced cognitive arousal
when chewing even tasteless,
sugarless gum,
though translational studies
on the acute cognitive effects
of gum chewing
are contradictory.
Maybe it's not the chewing,
though.
Noticing that people
missing molars
on one side of their mouths
have
asymmetrically-sized pupils,
a smaller pupil
on the missing molar side,
researchers tested whether
implanting dental crowns
to replace the missing teeth
could reduce the discrepancy,
and it did.
The study, subtitled "New Teeth
for a Brighter Brain,"
suggested that a gap
in the sensation of teeth
pushing against one another
adversely affects
brain function.
To put it to the test,
we'd want to randomize
people with missing teeth
to get dentures
and see if their cognition
improves over those who don't.
No such studies exist,
but there was an intriguing
pilot study performed.
Ten toothless individuals,
9 out of 10 of them
cognitively impaired,
6 of them severely so,
were given conventional dentures
for a month
before being fitted
with overdentures,
which are snapped
into titanium implants
surgically screwed
into the jawbone.
The conventional dentures,
held in place by adhesives
and natural suction,
did nothing to significantly
alter cognitive function.
But the ones securely attached
to implants in the bone,
presumably transmitting
the same kind
of chewing pressure sensations
to the nerves in the jaw
that natural roots
of teeth might,
had a dramatic effect.
Nine out of ten
of the subjects
went into the study
cognitively impaired,
but 8 out of 10 left the study
cognitively intact.
This suggests well-fitting,
secure dental prosthesis
isn't just about improving
self-confidence,
social contact,
quality of life,
but proper brain functioning
as well.
Of course, even better, though,
would be to preserve
the teeth you have.
In our next story,
we look at what would happen
if you stopped brushing your teeth
but ate healthier.
Experimentally, if you have people
stop brushing their teeth,
plaque starts to
build up and within
a few days the gums
start to get inflamed.
You can’t see anything yet,
but if you take a
biopsy at the gum line
you can see the inflammation
starting to spread,
and within a few weeks
overt gingivitis
becomes apparent,
where your gums can get
red, swollen, and bleed easily.
And if you don’t do
anything about it,
you can develop periodontal disease,
where the inflammation
creeps down into
the supporting structures of the tooth—
the bone and ligaments--
setting you up for tooth loss.
OK, but how did we get along
for millions of years
without brushing?
Yeah, dental disease is
almost universal these days,
but thousands of years
before the invention
of the toothbrush there are
skulls with perfect teeth.
Now, you can say:
“yeah, but that was also
thousands of years before the
invention of candy bars,”
but you don’t know until...
you put it to the test.
OK, yeah, but where
are you going to find
people to not only stop brushing
but also to forgo eating processed junk?
Security guards.
That‘s how you do it.
It was one of these
survivor-type TV shows
where people were forced to
live under stone-age conditions;
so no toothbrushes,
toothpaste, dental floss,
toothpicks, or other oral
hygiene products for a month.
Now they could use
a twig or something
but they were pretty
much on their own.
But, no candy bars either.
They were going for about 4,000 BC;
so lots of whole grains,
with supplemental salt,
herbs, honey, milk, and meat,
and then they could go
out and pick berries
or see what they could catch.
So, what happened?
With no oral hygiene
their plaque built up,
but their gums got healthier.
This is measuring BOP,
bleeding on probing
(whether or not your gums bled
when poked with a dental tool),
a measure of gingivitis;
and in almost every
case they got better.
Many of the more
disease-causing bacteria
seemed to have disappeared
from their mouths.
They suggest this could be
from the lack of refined sugars,
but they were eating honey;
so it wasn’t a
a sugar-free diet.
Ah, but what they
were eating was lots
of whole grains and berries
rich in antioxidant phytonutrients
with anti-inflammatory properties.
So, maybe it was a combination:
sugar intake restriction combined with
the intake of really healthy foods.
Thus, all those experimental
studies where people stop brushing
and their gums inevitably get inflamed
may only be applicable
for people eating
lots of processed foods rich in sugar
and low in anti-inflammatory
whole plant foods.
What about the role of
nutrition in periodontal health?
Gingivitis can lead to periodontitis,
an inflammatory disease
of the supporting tissues
of the teeth, which if untreated,
can lead to the progressive
loss of the bone
that holds the teeth in place.
Now, part of the development
of periodontal disease
may involve oxidative stress;
so, not only do we need
to reduce our intake
of pro-inflammatory foods like
refined carbs and saturated fats,
maybe it would help
if we sought out foods
that are antioxidant rich.
So, is there an association
between dietary vitamin C intake,
for example, with periodontitis?
Apparently so, with
increasing risk of periodontitis
associated with lower
levels of vitamin C intake,
but you don’t know until...
you put it to the
test to figure out
what effect vitamin C
depletion and supplementation
would have on periodontal health.
They basically locked
everyone up for three months
so they can provide
controlled amounts
of vitamin C and measures
of gum inflammation
were directly related
to their vitamin C status.
On about one orange
worth of vitamin C
their gums improved,
but then down to 5 mg
a day they got worse,
but then on 10 oranges worth
a day they got better,
and then worse again
when back down to 5.
Pretty convincing, though 5 mg
a day is like scurvy level.
I mean we know that
your gums start bleeding,
your teeth could fall out
when you have scurvy
but that doesn’t mean
taking extra helps.
And indeed, 1,500 mg
of vitamin C a day
did not seem to help prevent gingivitis.
And even 2,000 a day failed to
help periodontitis sufferers.
Maybe vitamin C is just too
weak of an antioxidant?
OK, what about lycopene, the
powerful antioxidant pigment
that makes tomatoes red?
It worked!
But that was from
injecting the stuff directly
into the gum pocket with a syringe.
Does it work if you just eat it?
Let’s find out.
A randomized, placebo-
controlled clinical trial
on the efficacy of lycopene
in the treatment of gingivitis.
Two weeks of less than a
single tomato-a-day’s worth
of lycopene versus
placebo for two weeks
both along with the
standard dental treatment,
which helped—a 10 to 20%
reduction in gingivitis
in the placebo group,
but nearly 30% improvement
within just one week
in the lycopene group.
And this was just like
the amount of lycopene
found in a teaspoon and a
half of tomato paste a day.
Totally doable.
OK, so tomatoes may help with gingivitis.
What about periodontitis?
Another randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
again treated with
usual dental cleaning
plus either that one
tomato-a-day’s worth
of lycopene or a placebo
for two months and…
significant improvements in
plaque gingivitis and bleeding,
though not probe pocket
depth and clinical attachment.
They conclude that
supplementation with lycopene
seems to have augmented
the healing sequence
of inflamed gingival tissues.
OK, but that was with a
whole tomato’s worth a day.
How about half-a-tomato’s worth,
or just three-quarters of a teaspoon
of tomato paste worth of lycopene a day?
it didn’t work, no difference,
so looks like you have
to go the whole tomato.
Finally today,
plant-based diets are put to the test
in the treatment of periodontal disease.
What's the effect of nutrition
on periodontal disease?
Periodontal disease is a
bacterial infection that results
in inflammatory destruction of
the connective tissue and bone
that supports the teeth,
and is therefore one of the leading
causes of our teeth falling out.
Like most infections though, how our
body responds may play a critical role.
Yes, the presence of bacteria
is the primary cause,
but a susceptible host is also
necessary for disease initiation.
The standard explanation of periodontal
disease is the plaque theory:
the buildup of plaque leads to
gingivitis, gum inflammation,
which leads to periodontitis,
inflammation lower down
beneath the gums.
But in some forms
of periodontal disease plaque
doesn't appear to play a critical role.
Therefore, in the last few years,
there's been more interest
in the importance of systemic
health, our body's response.
In this respect, nutrition may
be of great importance
since it's been implicated in a number
of other inflammatory diseases,
all of which carry elevated
periodontal disease risk.
Traditionally, when we think of the
effects of nutrition on dental diseases,
we're only thinking about cavities.
However, there's been less research on
the role of diet in periodontal diseases.
Well, if it's about inflammation, one
would expect saturated fat-rich diets
to make things worse,
increasing oxidative stress
as well inflammation,
so we may want to cut down
on saturated fat.
But, look, let's not just speculate.
I mean is there an association between
cholesterol levels and periodontitis?
If not, it would be hard
to implicate saturated fat.
But no, there does
appear to be a link.
Those with high cholesterol do
appear to have up to double the risk.
What about periodontal
conditions in vegetarians?
A 100 vegetarians versus
non-vegetarians were studied,
and those eating vegetarian did
have better periodontal conditions
(less inflammation signs,
less periodontal damage,
and better dental home care).
However, it should be
considered that vegetarians
may not just be avoiding meat,
but are healthier in other ways,
like better dental home care.
But do people who eat more
saturated fat get more periodontitis?
Yes, about double the risk at
the highest levels of intake,
and this study was in Japan
where they eat less than half
the meat and dairy
compared to the US.
The only way to know for sure, though,
is to do an interventional trial
where you change people's
diets and see what happens.
In other words, you
have to put it to the test.
And bone loss was indeed
magnified by a diet
high in saturated fat
and cholesterol.
"A high-fiber, low-fat diet improves
periodontal disease markers"
in terms of probing depth,
clinical attachment loss,
and bleeding on probing—
all the standard measures.
And, of course, eating a healthier diet,
body weight, blood sugar control,
and systemic inflammation
improved as well.
Ah, but that complicates things.
Maybe their mouths got better just
because they lost so much weight?
You can improve
periodontal disease
with just bariatric surgery,
like stomach stapling.
Well, after eight weeks on the diet,
they went back on their regular diet
and so gained most
of that weight back,
but the periodontal disease
improvements persisted, suggesting
that it was more than just the weight
loss that lead to the improvements.
They're thinking maybe the high-fiber
diet altered their good gut flora,
or maybe their oral flora?
What exactly was going on?
Well, German researchers
took 20 women with mild
to moderate chronic periodontitis,
and for a year tried
to transition their diets
towards more wholesome nutrition,
meaning more plant foods,
more whole foods, more fresh foods,
trying to center their diets around
vegetables and fruit,
whole grains, potatoes,
and legumes—beans, split
peas, chickpeas and lentils.
And after 12 months, the patients
showed a significant reduction
of probing pocket depth,
gingival inflammation,
and measured for the first time
decreased concentrations
of inflammatory chemicals inside the
crevice between the tooth and gums,
which are thought responsible
for the tissue destruction
in periodontal disease, a
decrease by as much as 75%.
And all the while, their oral
hygiene status didn't change,
suggesting it was
the diet that did it.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.